So we're picking up
today
from today's
דף daf is י"ז. yud-zayin. We're going to just start a little
bit before on י"ז עמוד ב', yud-zayin amud-bet, more I understand, about
right about where חזר בה רבי יהודה. Chazar bah Rabbi Yehuda. Is
that correct?
Correct, חזר בה רבי יהודה. Chazar bah Rabbi Yehuda.
Right, okay. So anyway let's just review for a moment.
So our
issue, our דיון, diyun, we were trying to figure out in a
case of ספק, safek, so and then it's a משקין טמאים mashkin
tmayim and then this משקה טמא mashkeh tamei came in contact with
something else. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that it's טהור tahor because
he basically says that the whole טומאת משקין tum'at mashkin is מדרבנן
mid'rabbanan anyway, so since it's a ספיקא מדרבנן sefeika mid'rabbanan then we're
more lenient. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says just the opposite,
so again this whole thing is טמא, tamei, but nevertheless he's saying
both, at least that's what we thought he started out saying, or
that's what he did start out saying I should say. In רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda opinion
though, משקין mashkin are מטמאים mtam'im מדאורייתא, mi-d'oreita, so since it's a
ספיקא מדאורייתא sefeika mi-d'oreita it's לחומרא. l'chumra. So as רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is, you know, extreme if you will in his
קולא, kula, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is מחמיר machmir in his חומרא,
chumra, right? So then רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon sort of split their vote. So they say, well if it's
a food it's טמא מספק, tamei mi-safek, but if it's a כלי
kli then it's טהור מספק, tahor mi-safek, right? So you must have
to say then that or you would say then in their opinion
so משקין mashkin are מטמאים
אוכלין מדאורייתא, mtam'im ochlin mi-d'oreita, which is why we're מחמיר machmir in
a case of ספק, safek, but כלים kelim only מדרבנן, mid'rabbanan, right?
Then we got into this whole issue yesterday
with a problem in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda שיטה shita and then
we basically said okay fine, so he reversed himself. But the thing
is remember, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was the most מיקל, meikel,
right, and then you have the other two opinions, right, which were
sort of splitting their vote, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was the
most מחמיר machmir if you want to lay it out in terms
of
lenient to strict, right? So then רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was חוזר,
chozer, did he go back
one step, which means he may split his vote right like that
opinion we just said a second ago, or did he really reverse
himself and now he's even as lenient as רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
who says it's no problem at all? Understand that? That's our question
right now.
So
איבעיא להו מכלים הוא דהדר ביה או באוכלין כרבי יוסי ורבי שמעון
סבירא ליה, Ibayu lehu mi-kelim hu d'hadar beh o b'ochlin k'Rabbi Yose
v'Rabbi Shimon sevirah leh, so did
he basically split his vote essentially? So he's saying okay fine, you're
right, I have to reverse myself. כלים kelim is not a problem,
but nevertheless he still may hold that אוכלין ochlin are טמאים tamei
if they came in contact with these
משקין. mashkin. That's our question. או דילמא לגמרי הדר ביה כרבי מאיר,
O dilma legamrei hadar beh k'Rabbi Meir, or did he completely reverse
himself and now he says no problem at all and everything would
be טהור מספק tahor mi-safek just like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says?
So
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק תא שמע, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
t'shama,
let's try to figure this out. פרה ששתתה
מי חטאת,
Parah she-shateta
mei chatat, right? So
you have the waters of the מי חטאת mei chatat which you're
going to use to sprinkle on somebody. So we know the whole
paradox about that, that if you're טמא tamei you become טהור, tahor,
but if you're טהור tahor you become טמא, tamei, right?
Is that rare, right, is that what the פרה אדומה parah adumah
that they make it from?
They make it from the פרה אדומה.
parah adumah. So this was
a very rare commodity. Yeah, yeah,
so how could they leave it lying around?
Oh yeah, I mean this
is not
really a הלכה למעשה halacha l'ma'aseh practical kind of thing, this is
just, you know, more of a theoretical.
Wait, this is the פרה parah that's doing...
okay wait no, I'm going to explain the case. So I didn't
finish explaining the case, just one minute. So all I started out
by saying was you have the מי חטאת mei chatat which is
made from the אפר פרה אדומה efer parah adumah and the paradox
of this is that if you're טמא מת tamei met and you
come in contact with this and it's sprinkled on you, you become
טהור, tahor, but if you're טהור tahor and you touch this you're
טמא. tamei. So now our case is this regular פרה parah decided
it's thirsty, goes to the, instead of going to the trough it
goes to the פרה אדומה parah adumah אפר efer bowl. So it
starts lapping that stuff up,
and now you want to שחט shacht this פרה, parah, right? So
as far as I understand it, so you want to שחט shacht
this פרה, parah, right, and so now you have this meat of
this פרה parah that drank this
מי חטאת mei chatat with the אפר פרה אדומה efer parah adumah
and you know presumably some of this, it didn't, the water didn't
fully pass through this cow's digestive system. So that's the case.
There's no way to know that really.
Okay so that's our case, that's the גמרא. gemara. You're saying what
רש"י Rashi is saying?
No, but רש"י Rashi says, the issue is it's still inside. I
just said that.
But there's no way of knowing
unless you passed it out.
Okay anyway so as I said our case is
the water right away, you know it's already inside. Right, so it's
a matter of... How do you right away how do you if
you're standing there
how do you let her drink? If you're standing... I know, this
is more of a theoretical case, I mean once...
what? Why you keep it covered? It's a very precious thing.
Of course, I mean it's all a constructed case. Anyway, so the
point is, what I'm trying to tell you though is that this
מי חטאת Mei Chatat is an אב הטומאה, Av HaTumah, right? So
it's pretty strict. It's an אב הטומאה, Av HaTumah, not just like
a ראשון, Rishon, not just like a whatever. So it's an אב
הטומאה Av HaTumah under normal circumstances.
So meanwhile, as I mentioned, cases where you שחטed shacht this פרה
Parah before, you know, while its water is still inside of this
פרה Parah that drank up
this מי חטאת. Mei Chatat. Okay, so then what's the law? Is
it טמא Tamei the בשר Basar or is it טהור? Tahor? So
the ruling is בשרה טמא Basara Tamei and רבי יהודה אומר בטלו
במעיה. Rabbi Yehuda Omer batlu b'me'eha.
So he's saying no so it's a מחלוקת. machloket. So the first
case is the first ruling is that it's טמא Tamei and the
second case is no basically it's you know, it became בטל batel
inside the you know intestines of this cow that drank it all
up. So therefore the בשר Basar is טהור. Tahor. So think about
this, so this is a case that's משקין טמאים, Mashkin Tme'in, right?
And now meat, if you will, is touching it, right? So we
say טומאת משקין Tumat Mashkin is מטמא אוכל metame ochel or do
we not? Right? So but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the one
that says it isn't. So that seemingly would be an answer to
our question as to whether he חוזר בו chozer bo entirely or
not, right? Because if he's saying that if he only חוזר chozer
like one step, then he should say that okay כי לימא טהורים
ki leima tehorim but משקין Mashkin are טמאים. Tme'im. I mean אוכלין
Ochlin are טמאים. Tme'im. Right? That's what he should say. But what
is he saying here? He's saying אוכלין Ochlin are טהורים Tehorim because
he's saying בטלו במעיה. batlu b'me'eha. So that should be an answer
to our question, right? This is essentially משקין טמאים Mashkin Tme'in that
touch food. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying it's טהור. Tahor.
So if you say that the טומאה tumah of the מי חטאת
Mei Chatat operates the same
as an אב הטומאה, Av HaTumah, that's nice.
Well, מת Met is אבי אבות הטומאה, Avi Avot HaTumah, but this
is an אב הטומאה. Av HaTumah. It would operate the same way
as almost as a טמא מת. Tamei Met. Yeah. As opposed to
just you know, like a שרץ Sheretz or something. Well no, שרץ
Sheretz is an אב הטומאה Av HaTumah also. So you could say
basically it's like a שרץ Sheretz almost, interestingly enough. Yeah. Anyway, so
that's the answer to our question.
So I'll read it again. ואי סלקא דעתך מחילוקים הוא דהדר ביה
באוכלין כרבי יוסי ורבי שמעון סבירא ליה. v'ee salka dach'tach mechillukim hu
d'hadar beih b'ochlin k'rabbi yossi v'rabbi shimon savira lei. So if he
still holds that it should be טומאת אוכלין tumat ochlin like רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, אמאי בטלו במעיה לגמרי?
amai batlu b'me'eha l'gamri? Why? Why? נהי דטומאה חמורה לא מטמאו טומאה
קלה מיהא ניטמאו? nehi d'tumah chamura lo metamu tumah kala miha nitamu?
Okay, it should be like a light טומאה, tumah, right? It's not
like an אב הטומאה Av HaTumah anymore, so it should be still
טמא. Tamei.
מאי בטלו במעיה נמי בטלו מטומאה חמורה אבל טומאה קלה מטמאו. mai
batlu b'me'eha nami batlu mi'tumah chamura aval tumah kala metamu. No, okay,
so we're saying it doesn't mean it doesn't sound as it isn't
what it sounds like essentially is what we're saying.
So it's like a you know, טומאה קלה tumah kala is what
we're saying. So basically really he would hold that the בשר Basar
is טמא, Tamei, that's a טומאה קלה. tumah kala. טומאה חמורה Tumah
chamura would still mean that it can מטמא metame something else, right?
So basically what we're saying is it's no longer an אב הטומאה
Av HaTumah in there. So rather it's the water once it's in
this cow, it's you know, it's sort of like a ראשון Rishon
of some sort.
So what we're saying is, the point is, the question was why
you know, I understand that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was חוזר chozer
on something, right? So the question is he חוזר chozer all the
way, is he חוזר chozer partly? Is he חוזר chozer all the
way in like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, no טומאה, tumah, nothing, these
משקין mashkin can't be מטמא metame anything else at all,
or do we say that you know, maybe not. So it seems
like basically since he said that it's בטלו במעיה, batlu b'me'eha, that
means it can't be מטמא metame anything, right? So the גמרא Gemara
is saying okay wait, I understand that it
you know, that maybe it shouldn't be like an אב הטומאה Av
HaTumah anymore, right? But we might still say that like let's say
it was regular let's say it was regular
טמא Tamei stuff, not an אב הטומאה. Av HaTumah. So we should
still say that it can be מטמא metame something else, right?
If he's not חוזר. chozer. So we're saying no, okay, no, it
means that nevertheless it can't like, for instance, let's say we had
ראשון, שני, שלישי, רביעי, rishon, sheni, shelishi, revi'i, so this is now
downgraded a level, an אב, av, you know, the אב av now
became a ראשון rishon or something, right? But a ראשון Rishon can
still make a שני. sheni.
So that's what we're saying, that it should still you know... so
but it sounds like by saying בטלו, batlu, it doesn't do anything.
So that's basically our question. That's the טומאה חמורה tumah chamura
would be that it you know, it can transfer this a couple
you know ways. is further down, but a טומאה קלה, tumah kalah,
you know, he's saying that nevertheless it still does. And so the
point is that he's not saying בטלו batlu is it stops completely,
rather that it's no longer an אב, av, so that'd be a
טומאה חמורה, tumah chamurah, and now it's a, now it's a טומאה
קלה. tumah kalah. It's a, it's not an אב av anymore, but
it can still be, it can still be מטמא, metameh, we're trying
to say, or it can still be מטמא metameh the אוכלין. ochlin.
So just, Mike, how do you read those, those lines here where
it says מה בטלו במים לגמרי? ma batlu b'mayim legamrei?
Right, so what we're saying is it doesn't mean במים לגמרי. b'mayim
legamrei. It means לגמרי. legamrei.
So how do you read the, did you read the following line?
How'd you read that word? So what he's saying is that מה
בטלו במים, ma batlu b'mayim, when he says בטלו, batlu, that it's
nullified, it's, it's not nullified as if it stops and no longer
can be מטמא metameh anything, rather it's בטלו מטומאה חמורה, batlu mi'tumah
chamurah, it's not an אב הטומאה av hatumah anymore, but nevertheless it
still has טומאה קלה מטמאו. tumah kalah metamu. So it can still,
it still, it's not an אב, av, so call it let's say,
I mean it doesn't exactly explain what it is, but it's more
like let's say like a ראשון, rishon, a ראשון rishon can still
make a שני, sheni, right?
So it can still be מטמא, metameh, and this, what would the
שני... sheni... and it can still be מטמא metameh something else. And
in this case it's מטמא metameh the flesh of the פר par
that drank it up. So it can still be מטמא טומאת אוכלין,
metameh tumat ochlin, because this flesh that the פר par drank it
up is now slaughtered, now it's meat. So the water inside this
אפר פרה אדומה, efer parah adumah, the water with the מי חטאת,
mei chatat, with the אפר, efer, you know, is now no longer
an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, but let's call it a ראשון לטומאה.
rishon l'tumah. And the ראשון rishon now makes this בשר טמא, basar
tamei, because a ראשון rishon can do that, it's משקה. mashkeh.
I was just asking how you actually read the words.
Yeah, בטלו batlu means it's not, it's no longer an אב הטומאה,
av hatumah, essentially what they're saying. That's, that's how they're reading it.
I'm not asking you to explain it. I'm asking to read the
words to me.
Okay. בטלו מהני, batlu mihani, בטלו מטומאה חמורה, batlu mi'tumah chamurah, it's
בטל batel from a טומאה חמורה tumah chamurah to מטמא metameh something
else, but it's not בטל batel from טומאה קלה, tumah kalah, אבל
טומאה קלה מטמאו, aval tumah kalah metamu, it can still be מטמא
טומאה קלה. metameh tumah kalah.
So that, I hope that answered your question, but if not we're
going to go on.
So okay fine, but that's Rabbi Yehuda's opinion, right? And so then
what about the תנא קמא? Tana Kama? Because remember there's a מחלוקת
machloket between the תנא קמא Tana Kama and Rabbi Yehuda. So מכלל
דתנא קמא סבר טומאה חמורה נמי מטמאו? miklal d'Tana Kama savar tumah
chamurah nami metamu? Right? So if we're saying that Rabbi Yehuda's the
lenient opinion and he still holds it can מטמא metameh the בשר,
basar, the flesh of the cow that drank this all up, so
the תנא קמא Tana Kama who's more מחמיר, machmir, right,
then you should say it's a טומאה חמורה, tumah chamurah, so it
should still say it's an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. But if it's
an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, why is he saying בשרה טמא? besarah
tamei? Right? Which if it's an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, it should
also be able to מטמא כלים. metameh keilim. So
why is he only saying the בשר basar is טמא? tamei? He
should say טמא, tamei, right? Why בשרה טמא, besarah tamei, which is
a qualifier? So then we're saying it can't be. So כולה רבי
יהודה היא. kula Rabbi Yehuda hi.
So no. So now we're saying actually there is no תנא קמא
Tana Kama versus Rabbi Yehuda. Although Rabbi Yehuda is if you will
cited as the second opinion, it's really all his opinion.
So how does it work? חסורי מחסרא. chasorei mechasra. So that means
we're, you know, read it as if like we've got to add
in a few words to make this make sense. So what is
our case? Let's go back. פרה ששתתה מי חטאת. parah she'shat'tah mei
chatat.
That's our case. בשרה טמא. besarah tamei. So so far we're keeping
what we just said. במה דברים אמורים? bameh devarim amurim? Oh, when
is בשרה טמא besarah tamei or
how, in what kind of case is it? It's a טומאה קלה.
tumah kalah. אבל טומאה חמורה לא, aval tumah chamurah lo, but it
can't be מטמא metameh something else like כלים. keilim. שרבי יהודה אומר
בטלו במים, she'Rabbi Yehuda omer batlu b'mayim, because Rabbi Yehuda says it's
בטלו במים, batlu b'mayim, right? But as we explained, it's בטלו במים
batlu b'mayim in terms of טומאה חמורה, tumah chamurah, but it still
has טומאה קלה. tumah kalah. So all this is Rabbi Yehuda's opinion.
So basically saying that Rabbi Yehuda's explaining himself. You can see this
explanation somewhat unnecessary, it would have been more elegant to just say
it all right out, you know, Rabbi Yehuda says, right, it really
would have been better to just have said Rabbi Yehuda says that
פרה ששתתה מי חטאת, parah she'shat'tah mei chatat, you know, יש לו
טומאה קלה, yesh lo tumah kalah, that's all, you know, that's really
what it could have said, but whatever we're being somewhat more circumlocutory
and basically it's all Rabbi Yehuda's opinion and we're saying he only
has, it only has טומאה קלה tumah kalah
insofar as it can be מטמא metameh the בשר basar but not
anything else like let's say כלים. keilim. So okay
so that, so basically what we just said over here is that
בטלו batlu doesn't really mean בטלו, batlu, but rather בטלו batlu means
it's not as severe, but it can still be, it can still
be מטמא. metameh. An alternative, you know, you can still say that
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, no, לעולם בטלו במים לגמרי, le'olam
batlu b'mayim legamrei, keep what it says, you know, don't try to
if you will
reinterpret the
פשט pshat
of the text, which sounds like בטלו batlu means בטלו. batlu. Okay,
but what do you, so if he says בטלו, batlu, then we
would still think that it would answer our question, right? בטלו batlu
means completely בטל. batel. That means
Rabbi
Yehuda... don't know that he would go so far as to reverse
himself and be as מקל mekal as רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because
משום דהוי ליה משקה סרוח. mishum dehavai lei mashkeh saruach. This is
different. I mean, this isn't a regular, you know, משקה mashkeh that's
just kind of sitting out there, like you know, your cup of
coffee. This is water that was swallowed by a cow, right? So
once it's in this cow, it's like, you know, it's almost like
not considered a משקה mashkeh anymore. It's, you know, passed through the
digestive system or it's somewhere sitting in the digestive system of this
cow, and now it's משקה סרוח, mashkeh saruach, it's, you know, disgusting.
So once,
yeah, it's not like משקה mashkeh anymore basically. So you know, טומאה
tumah doesn't apply. You know, just like you know, just if something,
an אוכל ochel is become putrefied in such an extent that it's
not ראוי לאכילת כלב, raui l'achilat kelev, you know, then we don't
say that there's תורת חמץ torat chametz on it anymore, you know,
or so other laws also are of similar nature that once something
is not considered to be in its state anymore, then
leniencies
can be exercised. So basically what we're saying is that this פרה
parah case is different and we wouldn't know what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda would say in a regular case, if, how much he'd be
חוזר. chozer. So רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's revised opinion is now somewhat
in the air.
Okay, fine.
So much for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So now we're going to
go to the last
opinion, רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים לאוכלין טמאין ולכלים טהורין. Rabbi Yose
v'Rabbi Shimon omrim l'ochlin tme'in ul'kelim tehorin. So they split their vote,
right? Remember רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda started off
by saying it's טומאה מדאורייתא, tumah m'deoraita, so therefore משקין mashkin are
מטמא. metame. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says they're not.
And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose or רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon split their
vote, לאוכלין טמאין ולכלים טהורין, l'ochlin tme'in ul'kelim tehorin, which means that
for מדאורייתא m'deoraita they can מטמא אוכלין, metamei ochlin. but
מדרבנן m'derabbanan טומאת כלים tumat kelim is מדרבנן, m'derabbanan, so therefore it's
a case of ספק safek and we will be more מקל mekal
in cases of כלים. kelim. So אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
ריש לקיש רבי יוסי,
Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Reish Lakish Rabbi Yose, right? Remember there are two people here, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So רבי יוסי בשיטת
רבי עקיבא רבו אמרה. Rabbi Yose b'shitat Rabbi Akiva rabo amrah. So
what he's going according to his, you know, the view of his
רבי, Rebbi, who is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And later on, we're
going to say that this is important, that רבי יוסי בשיטת רבי
עקיבא רבו אמרה. Rabbi Yose b'shitat Rabbi Akiva rabo amrah. He's seeing
it in the שיטה shita of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose may not actually agree with it. So he's quoting
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's opinion. Okay,
so דדריש יטמא. d'darish yitma. And then I should get out a
חומש Chumash over here. This is enough. Get this out.
The גמרא Gemara actually has the פסוקים psukim over there are very
useful. So let's get this out. So this is in ויקרא. Vayikra.
I'll read you two פסוקים psukim
because we're going to come back to this a number of times.
Okay,
so this is in פרשת שמיני Parshat Shmini where you have a
whole bunch of this stuff, you know, like animals you can eat
and what you can't eat. Then it talks about
things
like our case that we're going to be talking about today. So
it starts talking about the שרץ, sheretz, and then ובכל אשר יפול
עליו מהם במותם. v'chol asher yipol alav meihem b'motam.
So let's say this שרץ, sheretz, this dead שרץ sheretz now, drops
into some... a כלי, kli, right? מכל כלי עץ או בגד או
עור או שק וכל כלי אשר יעשה מלאכה בהם, mikol kli eitz
o beged o or o sak v'chol kli asher yeiaseh melachah bahem,
drops onto something, right? במותם. b'motam. And so
it drops onto whatever it is, you know, so it becomes טמא.
tame. Then במים יובא וטמא עד הערב וטהר. bamayim yuva v'tame ad
haerev v'taher. Okay, fine. וכל כלי חרס, v'chol kli cheres, this is
the more important part for today. So let's say it falls in,
it falls, as opposed to the first case where it falls on
something, like let's say you know, your leather jacket of some sort
becomes טמא. tame. But now this falls into a כלי חרס, kli
cheres, and this כלי חרס kli cheres has something else in it,
right? וכל כלי חרס אשר יפול מהם אל תוכו.
v'chol kli cheres asher yipol meihem
el tocho. So
this dead שרץ sheretz drops into this כלי, kli, forget about water
for the moment, but כל אשר בתוכו יטמא. kol asher b'tocho yitma.
So
it drops into the כלי, kli, there's food in there, everything's in
there, everything in there is... What?
It has to be a liquid to make טומאה tumah transmit the
טומאה. tumah.
Why?
It's in
the כלי
חרס. kli cheres.
It
has to be a liquid. No, this is a כלי חרס. kli
cheres.
This is a כלי חרס, kli cheres, so the כלי חרס kli
cheres is מטמא מאווירו, metame mei'aviro, right? Sort of like you know,
we had these cases of ovens too, like you know, טומאה's's tumah
in the oven and then the whole oven becomes טמא tame and
the food that's in it becomes... it's a degree removed, right?
Why? I thought you need
a
liquid on
something or at some point to make the טומאה tumah
to transmit the... Let's say I pluck my fruit. Let's say let's
say the fruit's on the tree. Let's say let's say the fruit
is on the tree, right? No matter how many times water came
on it, then then nothing will make it טמא tamei because it's
still, you know, it's still attached to whatever it was. Let's say
I take it off, right? And then and then a dead שרץ
sheretz falls on it.
And a שרץ sheretz has to be dead to be to be
מטמא?
metame
Yeah, always.
In other words, yeah, live things are not מטמא. metamei? Only dead
things. Correct. I didn't think you need liquid, didn't we learn?
You need it to have had liquid on it at some point
after it was plucked. After it was plucked, but the liquid doesn't
doesn't need to be on it right now. But that's that's the
regular
case, like let's say a שרץ. sheretz. But how do you know
it was ever on it? Because
I left
it out, let's say, in the summer for four days, you know,
and and there's dew every night and then, you know, so you
know that the water came on it.
Dew is one of the things that are מטמא. metamei. Is there
water on the dead שרץ? sheretz? No, you don't need water on
the dead שרץ. sheretz. You just you know in a regular case
of אוכלין ochlin, to make it טמא tamei you need you needed
to have had, you know, let's say let's take your fruit, right?
You need to have had מים mayim go on the fruit, not
necessarily on the שרץ. sheretz. A שרץ, sheretz, a שרץ sheretz like
it's always טמא.
tamei. So how do you know there
was
מים mayim anyway on the fruit? Like again, like I said, like
you left it out for like, you know, four days outside and
and you know and it rained or dew even in the summer.
So can it also exude the liquid from inside of it,
like fruit juices and stuff like that? Fruit juices are not מים.
mayim. Oh, that's right. Everything else is מים. mayim.
So
but no, but I mean but this is a little bit of
this is a little bit of different. So meanwhile
let's read this
פסוק pasuk
again.
Okay, but our point is that there's food in in this כלי
חרס, kli cheres, right?
That is
now also now this כלי חרס kli cheres also has a שרץ,
sheretz, right? The שרץ sheretz doesn't need to touch the food, that's
the point. Although normal cases a שרץ sheretz need to touch needs
to touch the food, in the case of a of a כלי
חרס, kli cheres, the שרץ sheretz does not need to touch the
food. Just needs to you know let's say you dangle a dead
שרץ, sheretz, you know, somewhere by in the inside of a כלי.
kli. So the air is now מטמא metamei. and then this טומאה
tumah goes into goes to the food, right? That's in it.
Like in the case of a vat.
Yeah. So and and there's no way at all, let's say it
was another type of כלי, kli, you could at least מטהר metaher
the כלי, kli, but a כלי חרס kli cheres you can't מטהר,
metaher, you gotta break it. Right, then once it's no longer usable
you can still eat it but it's no longer usable.
So but again, yes, food doesn't need I was trying to draw
the distinction, the food needs to be מכשיר machshir through מים, mayim,
doesn't have to have the מים mayim on it now. Doesn't have
to be wet at this point. It's had to become wet at
some point.
It had to
have been wet.
But I'm not so sure that it ever was.
Well, I mean, let's say this is the case that it was.
So just you know it'll be complicated enough
in
the normal case. So okay fine, that's that's one thing. So right,
but so I'll read this פסוק pasuk again: מכל האכל אשר יאכל
אשר יבוא עליו מים יטמא, mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo alav
mayim yitma, right?
So this אוכל ochel our you know כלי חרס kli cheres case,
right? So has food in it,
let's say. So any food which מים mayim had come, doesn't be
wet now though, shall now be טמא. tamei. וכל משקה vechol mashkeh
the first one was אוכל, ochel, first thing is אוכל ochel now
וכל משקה אשר ישתה בכל כלי יטמא. vechol mashkeh asher yishateh vechol
kli yitma. So and if there's any you know liquid in it,
let's say it was a barrel of wine or something like that
then you have the שרץ sheretz in it,
that also becomes טמא. tamei. Okay? So remember יטמא יטמא. yitma yitma.
There are two so in this second פסוק pasuk I read that
it was was written is
יטמא yitma twice, right? I'll read it again: מכל האכל אשר יאכל
אשר יבוא עליו מים יטמא וכל משקה אשר ישתה בכל כלי יטמא.
mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo alav mayim yitma vechol mashkeh asher
yishateh vechol kli yitma. Right? Hear that twice? Once is אוכל, ochel,
one is for משקה. mashkeh.
So but however as we all know the Torah does not have
ניקוד, nikkud, right? So יטמא yitma is more passive, right? It shall
become טמא. tamei. That's what that means, right? But if you read
it, vocalize it a little bit different, you can get יטמא, yetamei,
right? And יטמא yetamei means it makes something else טמא, tamei, right?
So
getting back to this,
so רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, I'll read it
again: אוכלין טמאין לכדים טהורין. ochlin temei'in lekadim tehorin. So אוכלין ochlin
was what we were talking about, right? So אוכלין ochlin is our
case over here. In the Torah is what we're talking about, אוכל,
ochel, מים, mayim, right? All these kind of things, משקה, mashkeh, right?
The יטמא. yitma. Oh right. Yeah, yeah, yeah. יטמא. yitma. Right, so
right.
So he says דרשינן יטמא יטמא. darshinan yitma yetamei. Right, so
basically a
something that's a טמא tamei food, right? If it's יטמא, yetamei, so
it can make something else טמא. tamei. That's what יטמא yetamei means.
So He basically also holds
that let’s say this משקין, mashkin, but again, there is a case
of a שרץ, sheretz, right?
So just like it says יטמא יטמא, yitma yitamei, so too in
משקין, mashkin, so basically, he holds that יטמא. yitamei. So remember our
whole point was can משקין mashkin be מטמא metamei anything? So he
says yes they can, but you know since we have these יטמא
יטמא yitma yitamei vocalization, so too by
apply this to משקין, mashkin, יטמא יטמא. yitma yitamei. משקין mashkin can
make something else be מטמא, metamei can make something else become טמא.
tamei. What is it? So okay, fine. So he’s saying that it
depends what it is. משקין mashkin can make אוכל ochel become טמא,
tamei, which is you know all these פסוקים pesukim we’re talking about
אוכל. ochel. But they can’t let’s say make כלים keilim become טמא.
tamei. Right? That’s their opinion. So they דרשן darshen it from what
we just were mentioning.
Okay, anyway, so we said this is עקיבא'ס Akiva’s שיטה shitta to
דרשן darshen יטמא יטמא, yitma yitamei, דתנן בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא,
detnan bo bayom darash Rabbi Akiva, וכל כלי חרש אשר יפל מהם
vechol kli cheres asher yipol mehem
which is what I was reading, אינו אומר טמא, eino omer tamei,
right
it doesn’t say if you look at it, I’ll read it again,
וכל כלי חרש אשר יפל מהם אל תוכו כל אשר בתוכו vechol
kli cheres asher yipol mehem el tocho kol asher betocho it could
have said טמא, tamei, right? Whatever’s in there is טמא. tamei. But
it says יטמא. yitma. Which if you take it in the passive
‘shall become טמא’ tamei is the same thing, but the question is
then why does it say יטמא? yitma? It would have been more
simple to say טמא. tamei. That’s the way it’d be usually mentioned.
But it says יטמא. yitma. So he’s saying although we read it
יטמא, yitma,
we say יטמא, yitamei, right? And maybe the reason why it does
it that way is according to this opinion because it can’t be
מטמא metamei, everything, right? It can’t be מטמא metamei כלים, keilim, but
only be מטמא metamei אוכלין. ochlin So therefore it’s sort of like
passive and sort of active, right? You get that? Since it doesn’t
say טמא, tamei, טמא tamei would be totally passive, it can’t be
מטמא metamei anything. But it doesn’t say, you know, but it
doesn’t—it’s not said as in יטמא, yitamei, it could be vocalized יטמא.
yitamei. So therefore, you know, you sort of have that dichotomy between
the קרי kri and the כתיב, ktiv, so it can be מטמא
metamei somewhat, right? אוכלין ochlin. but not כלים. keilim. So יטמא אחרים,
itamei acherim, he’ll make a ככר שני kikar sheni which makes a
שלישי shlishi in חולין, chullin, so okay, so anyway he’s saying a
ככר kikar let’s say you have the whole levels of טומאה, tuma,
so it can be מטמא, metamei so in חולין chullin it can
go into a שלישי shlishi even in חולין, chullin, right? So
we’ve had until now שלישי בתרומה shlishi be’teruma and a רביעי בקדשים.
revii be’kodshin. He’s saying even
a שלישי בחולין shlishi be’chullin which is somewhat of a חידוש chiddush
here, which is why we’re going to say that not necessarily everyone
would agree with Rabbi עקיבא, Akiva, right? The concept is there, right?
Because Rabbi יוסי Yose and Rabbi שמעון Shimon are saying conceptually it
can be מטמא metamei, אוכלין ochlin but not כלים, keilim, right? So
but Rabbi יוסי'ס Yose’s not going to agree with Rabbi עקיבא Akiva
insofar as how far you take it. But that’s why we’re saying
he said the שיטה, shitta, the gist of it,
the underlying לימוד limud is there that you learn יטמא, yitamei, but
as to how far you take it is a matter of dispute.
Okay, fine. והכא היכי דרש vehecha heichi darash וכל משקה אשר ישתה
בכל כלי יטמא. vechol mashkeh asher yeshateh bechol kli yitma. So again
יטמא, yitamei, to מטמא metamei
טומאת אוכלין. tum’at ochlin. So that’s basically what we’re saying, is it
to מטמא metamei טומאת אוכלין tum’at ochlin or to מטמא metamei טומאת
משקין? tum’at mashkin? Okay,
well how do you know? Again, there are a couple of ways
you can have things, you can have a משקה, mashkeh, you can
have an אוכל, ochel, you can have a כלי, kli, right? So
he’s saying no, it’s only to מטמא metamei טומאת אוכלין. tum’at ochlin.
Not כלים, keilim, not משקין, mashkin, right? So if a משקה mashkeh
that’s טמא tamei touches another משקה mashkeh it won’t make it טמא.
tamei.
If a משקה mashkeh that’s טמא tamei touches an אוכל, ochel, it
will make it טמא. tamei. If a משקה mashkeh that’s טמא tamei
touches a כלי, kli, it will not make it טמא. tamei.
So in the hierarchy of things susceptible to טומאה, tuma, אוכלין ochlin
are the easiest and then משקין mashkin is more difficult and כלים
keilim are more difficult.
I wouldn’t necessarily say that, I mean כלים keilim are definitely more
difficult, right? In terms of משקין mashkin and אוכלין, ochlin
we’ll see that it may appear the reason why I’m hedging is
because the גמרא'ס Gemara’s going to get to it. The גמרא’s Gemara
going to say the whole reason even if אוכלין ochlin, appear easier,
it’s because of משקין mashkin anyway. So I’m not going to answer
that right now. כלים keilim are more difficult, we’ll say that, yeah.
Okay anyway, so the point is, so okay fine, we understand if
you’re reading this יטמא yitma as in
יטמא, yitamei, these משקין mashkin can be מטמא metamei something, right? So
what is it? Right? כלי, kli, other משקה, mashkeh, other אוכל? ochel?
So he said his לימוד limud was טומאת אוכלין. tum’at ochlin. So
we’re saying how do you know? אתה אומר לטמא טומאת אוכלין או
אינו אלא לטמא טומאת משקין? Atomer letamei tum’at ochlin o eino ela
letamei tum’at mashkin? What, you know, how do you know it’s not
maybe think like can מטמא metamei like, right?
משקין mashkin can מטמא metamei other משקין, mashkin, but it can’t מטמא
metamei an אוכל. ochel. How do you know?
No, we can’t say it can be מטמא metamei טומאת משקין tum’at
mashkin because לאו כהייא. lo kachaya. It can’t be that way. What
do you mean—the גמרא’s Gemara going to say it can’t because it
can’t? What kind of tautology is that? מאי לאו כהייא? Mai lo
kachaya? What do you mean, why not?
It can’t, that’s not the way it’s meant to be. אמר רב
פפא Amar Rav Papa what do we mean by לאו כהייא lo
kachaya means לא מצינו טומאה. lo matzinu tuma. No, what he's saying
is לא מצינו טומאה עושה כיוצא בה lo matzinu tumah osah kayotzei
bah because we don't see that a טומאה tumah makes something else
like it טמא tamei like it. So in other words we don't
see anywhere that an אוכל ochel is מטמא metamei an אוכל ochel
or a משקה mashkeh is מטמא metamei a משקה. mashkeh. No, rather
a משקה mashkeh is מטמא metamei an אוכל. ochel. So that's what
he's saying, and we're going to explain this.
So רבינא אמר מגופיה דקרא נמי לא מצית אמרת. Ravina amar migufeh
dekra nami lo matzit amrat. So even from the פסוק pasuk we've
been talking about this whole time about יטמא yitma יטמא. yitameh. So
what are you going to say, that יטמא yitma is מטמא טומאה
דמשקין? metamei tumah de'mashkin? So basically what you're trying to say is
our whole question was what is it מטמא? metamei A משקה mashkeh
מטמא metamei? other משקין mashkin or מטמא metamei אוכלין. ochlin So if
you're going to say this יטמא yitma is מטמא טומאה דמשקין, metamei
tumah de'mashkin,
so fine, דסלקא דעתך יטמא דסיפא לטמא טומאה דמשקין, de'isalka da'atach yitma
de'seifa letamei tumah de'mashkin, remember there were two parts to this, this
פסוק. pasuk. I'll read it again: מכל האוכל אשר יאכל אשר יבוא
עליו מים יטמא. mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo alav mayim yitma.
So that's אוכל. ochel. Then וכל משקה אשר ישתה בכל כלי יטמא,
ve'chol mashkeh asher yeshateh be'chol kli yitma, right? Then there's משקה. mashkeh.
So if you're trying to say this משקה mashkeh that goes into
a כלי kli is מטמא metamei when we say יטמא yitma as
in it's מטמא metamei something else is it now משקין, mashkin, right?
That's the סיפא. seifa. So if the סיפא seifa we're saying that
this משקין mashkin is מטמא metamei another משקה, mashkeh, okay fine. Then
what about the first part? Then יטמא דרישא נמי לטמא טומאה דמשקין?
yitma de'reisha nami letamei tumah de'mashkin? So
are we going to say מכל האוכל אשר יאכל אשר יבוא עליו
מים יטמא? mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo alav mayim yitma? Are
you going to try to say that it's also מטמא טומאה דמשקין?
metamei tumah de'mashkin? That foods, what we mean by that is that
foods also... so if we're saying that this substance is מטמא metamei
something else, right? So then this אוכל ochel can be מטמא metamei
something else, right? Because מכל האוכל אשר יאכל אשר יבוא עליו מים
יטמא. mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo alav mayim yitma. So מים
mayim falls on this אוכל. ochel. This אוכל ochel now since we
said יטמא yitma doesn't mean it's only becoming טמא tamei but can
be מטמא metamei something else, right? Just like the מים mayim that
became טמא tamei can be מטמא metamei something else. And if you're
saying the thing it can be making טמא tamei is משקה, mashkeh,
right? If we're saying that the end part is now משקה, mashkeh,
then what does this אוכל ochel מטמא? metamei? Is this אוכל ochel
also מטמא משקה? metamei mashkeh? Right? So then if you're saying that
the אוכל ochel is also מטמא משקה metamei mashkeh then you have
basically you've constructed your cases that משקין mashkin and אוכלין ochlin are
מטמא משקה, metamei mashkeh, right? That's what we just said. That if
we're saying what can it be מטמא, metamei, משקה, mashkeh, and if
we're saying the end is משקה, mashkeh, and then if we're saying
the beginning is משקה, mashkeh, if you're going to say that, we're
not saying we're going to say that, but if you're going to
say that, then why do you have to say מכל האוכל אשר
יאכל אשר יבוא עליו מים mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo alav
mayim and then וכל משקה ve'chol mashkeh then יטמא? yitma? Why say
this יטמא yitma twice? Just make it one big case.
Why would it have to do this on purpose?
Wait, wait, we'll get to it. That
לערבינהו ולכתבינהו, le'arbevinhu ve'lichtivinhu,
right? מכל האוכל אשר יאכל אשר יבוא עליו מים mikol ha'ochel asher
ye'achel asher yavo alav mayim או וכל משקה אשר ישתה בכל כלי
o ve'chol mashkeh asher yeshateh be'chol kli then יטמא, yitma, right? Why
do you have these two יטמאs, yitma right? Could have said whether
it's food or drink then יטמא. yitma. Right? Whether food or drink
it's יטמא. yitma. And what is יטמא? yitma? It's מטמא metamei something
else, another משקה, mashkeh, right? That's what we're saying, that's what you're
trying to say. That if you're going to say that a beverage,
a משקה, mashkeh, can מטמא metamei another משקה, mashkeh, then all on
this whole פסוק pasuk is talking about מטמא משקין. metamei mashkin. So
whether a food or whether a liquid can be מטמא metamei another
משקה mashkeh then just make one big פסוק, pasuk, whether a food
or or a liquid can be מטמא. metamei. Don't say whether a
food it's מטמא metamei or whether a liquid it's מטמא. metamei. Why
do you need this יטמא yitma twice? Right?
Okay, so what? So תרי יטמא למה לי? trei yitma lamah li?
אלא יטמא דרישא לטמא טומאה דמשקין ויטמא דסיפא לטמא טומאה דאוכלין. ella
yitma de'reisha letamei tumah de'mashkin ve'yitma de'seifa letamei tumah de'ochlin. So now
they're two different cases, right? So the first part of the פסוק
pasuk is that if
any food that now מים mayim comes on it, יטמא, yitma, it
becomes... it
itself becomes טמא tamei and it can be מטמא metamei something else.
What can the food be מטמא? משקין. metamei mashkin Okay, now the
end is וכל משקה אשר ישתה בכל כלי. ve'chol mashkeh asher yeshateh
be'chol kli. If now this טמא משקה tamei mashkeh falls on, gets
in there, and
makes something else טמא, tamei, because that's what יטמא yitma means, can
make something else טמא. tamei. What? אוכלין. ochlin. So משקין mashkin. can
make אוכלין ochlin טמא tamei and אוכלין ochlin can make משקה mashkeh
טמא. tamei. So that's why you need two יטמאs, yitma because it's
two different things. One יטמא yitma is to teach you food for
an אוכל, ochel, and the other יטמא yitma is אוכל ochel for
a drink... אוכל ochel for a drink, right? So then I understand
why you have two, why you have two טומאות, tumos, right? So
okay. So means, so basically what we just said is, and that's
what he said before, that we don't see anything that can make
itself טמא. tamei. We don't see an אוכל ochel making אוכל ochel
or משקה mashקה making משקה. mashקה.
No, we've had case after case at the beginning of the סוגיא
sugya talking earlier about טומאה... tumah... תרומה טמאה
terumah teme'ah falling into תרומה טהורה
terumah tehorah etc. It was the same מין במינו. min be'mino. I
don't understand. רב פפא Rav Papa saying מין במינו min be'mino is
not מטמא? metamei?
It's interesting whether you can make it בטל batel or not, right?
In other words, why am I, because I don't know which is
the תרומה טמאה terumah teme'ah or the תרומה טהורה. terumah tehorah.
I understand that, but does he... do I understand this correctly that
he's saying... That the same kind of food cannot make its own
kind טמא? tamei?
That's what I understand him as saying, right?
We never have, have we not seen case after case in which
the same types of food, one is טמא tamei and one is
טהור, tahor, one is ספק טמא safek tamei and one is טהור,
tahor, and they come into contact with each other and the question
is whether it's בטל batel or not? In other words, ביטול, bitul,
right?
Because you don't know, I don't think we're saying, because you don't
know which one of them it is. If I have תרומה, trumah,
I can't eat תרומה טמאה, trumah temeiah, is
he saying in principle, the principle, oatmeal טמא tamei comes into contact
with oatmeal טהור tahor and there's no problem because it's the same
thing?
I think so, right? But the problem is if, but the
problem is our problems before, right? Correct me if I'm wrong, where
problems before you have תרומה, trumah,
your case of תרומה, trumah, right, טהור, tahor, טמא, tamei, whatever, they
got mixed up with each other, right? The problem is I can't
eat תרומה טהורה? trumah tehorah? Okay, so do I apply the cases
of ביטול? bitul? Can't eat תרומה טמאה. trumah temeiah.
Correct, right? I can't eat תרומה טמאה. trumah temeiah. I can, you
know, I can burn it. But the problem is, okay, but I
don't know which of this is the טמא. tamei. It's not that
I'm saying it's all טמא. tamei. Problem is case of ביטול. bitul.
So then you have to, you know, operate along those lines. I
don't think it was an issue of טומאה tumah as much, right?
Never understood that like that before. I really appreciate that. In other
words, you're telling me according to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, I don't
know if this is universally held, but according to this idea, never
understood it like that. Fantastically clarified. I have a whole barrel of
wheat and,
and טמא tamei wheat falls into it.
Essentially, according to this, is I've got separate kernels of טמא tamei
and טהור tahor wheat?
I just don't know which is which.
Right, but I just don't know which one is it.
Right, that's the way I'm understanding it.
It's not that the entire barrel has now become טמא tamei because
it's come into contact.
Correct, right. I never thought of that. I'm sorry if everyone else
understood it.
No, I mean, I maybe I'm wrong, but that's the way I'm
understanding it according to this רב פפא. Rav Pappa. I don't see
how any other way of understanding it.
Right, correct. That's why I stopped. It ground to a halt. Yeah,
it's astounding. It also sounds like it's universal, that's not challenged.
No.
So, okay, anyway, so the point is, so now we've at least
gotten so far as saying that a משקה mashkeh will not make
another משקה mashkeh טמא, tamei, right? But the problem is though we
don't, so we still have two יטמא yitmas and יטמא, yitamis, whatever,
right? So remember, there were three, if you will, there are three
categories. There's משקין, mashkin there's אוכלין, ochlin, and then there's also כלים.
kelin. So I understand you're saying it can't make another משקה mashkeh
טמא, tamei, right?
But maybe, ואימא תטמא
את הכלים, ve-eima tamei et ha-kelin,
right? Okay fine, so can't be מטמא את המשקה, metamei et ha-mashkeh,
but maybe it can be מטמא את הכלים metamei et ha-kelin still?
Now about five lines up from the bottom. So now ולאו קל
וחומר הוא, ve-lav kal va-chomer hu, ומה כלי שמטמא משקה, u-mah keli
she-metamei mashkeh, אין מטמא כלי, ein metamei keli, right?
Remember this whole thing was in a משקה, mashkeh, in a כלי,
keli, right? That that was our whole point, the כלי חרס keli
cheres and you know, then something falls in it and what is
it מטמא, metamei? right? So ומה כלי שמטמא משקה, u-mah keli she-metamei
mashkeh, אין מטמא כלי, ein metamei keli, משקין הבאין מחמת כלי, mashkin
ha-ba'in machamat keli, אינו דין שלא יטמאו
את הכלים? eino din
she-lo yetamei et ha-kelin? So
we're saying it doesn't make sense to say the כלי keli is
טמא. tamei. Because this whole כלי חרס, keli cheres, right, where the
שרץ sheretz fell, it cannot be מטמא metamei, another one, right? That
we didn't see any of that, right?
Our whole question was אוכלין ochlin in it or משקין. mashkin, So
now you're saying משקין mashkin. that the whole reason it became טמא
tamei is because a שרץ sheretz fell in it, you know, into
this barrel containing oil, wine, whatever. So אינו דין שלא יטמאו את
הכלים. eino din she-lo yetamu et ha-kelin. Certainly the משקה mashkeh won't
be מטמא metamei the כלי. keli. The כלי keli can't be מטמא
metamei another כלי. keli. You're going to say the משקה mashkeh that's
in this כלי keli could be מטמא metamei the כלי? keli?
So okay, nevertheless, ואימא כי לא מטמאו משקין הבאין מחמת כלי, ve-eima
kielo metamu mashkin ha-ba'in machamat keli, אבל משקין הבאין מחמת שרץ הכא
נמי טמא. aval mashkin ha-ba'in machamat sheretz hacha nami tamei. Fine, okay.
So so fine, so say
that so I understand, so let's say I have,
so how do you know that the שרץ sheretz itself can't be
מטמא, metamei right? In other words,
let's say the שרץ sheretz fell into the משקה mashkeh itself, right?
הכא hacha so maybe that can be מטמא כלי? metamei keli? I
understand that if the שרץ sheretz falls into the כלי keli and
not necessarily touching the משקה, mashkeh, then the כלי keli itself becomes
טמא tamei and then the כלי keli has משקה mashkeh because remember,
you can dangle the dead שרץ sheretz over there, right? So so
the dead שרץ, sheretz, let's say it didn't touch, make it easier,
the dead שרץ sheretz didn't touch any of the משקה mashkeh but
it's in the airspace of the כלי. keli. The כלי keli is
now טמא tamei and then the משקה mashkeh are טמא tamei as
a result, right? So I understand in that case, it can't be
מטמא metamei, another כלי. keli. But how do I know that if
the שרץ sheretz directly touches this משקה, mashkeh, right, and now you
know it's a pool of water, it touches that, how do I
know that that can't be מטמא? metamei So basically I understand so
what we have so far is we've conclusively said that a משקה
mashkeh can't be טמא tamei another משקה mashkeh as a like can't
be מטמא metamei? like, right? Opposites repel, you know, like repels, right?
Opposites attract, right? Only opposites can be make טומאה. tumah. So how
do we know it's not כלי? kli? So no, no, it can't
be כלי kli because of this קל וחומר. kal vachomer. But the
קל וחומר kal vachomer only is in so far as that a
משקה mashke became טמא tamei in the airspace of a כלי, kli,
not necessarily touched by the שרץ. sheretz. But if the שרץ sheretz
touches it directly, how do I still know that that can't be
מטמא metamei כלים? keilim? Because remember, this is a case of, this
is רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose case. He says it can't be מטמא
metameh כלים. keilim. That was his whole point. We're all going according
to that opinion of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it can't be מטמא
metameh כלים, keilim, it can only be מטמא metameh אוכלין. ochlin. And
we're saying, how do we know it can't be מטמא metameh כלים?
keilim? I can construct a case, the גמרא Gemara is saying, that
it can be potentially מטמא metameh a כלי. kli. That is if
the שרץ sheretz itself directly falls into this משקה mashke and now
this משקה mashke touches the כלי. kli. How do I know even
then that it's not? Because that's his opinion that it's not.
How do we know even then that the משקה mashke is not
מטמא metameh the כלי kli even in the case where the שרץ
sheretz is in the משקה? mashke? Correct. Even in the case where
the שרץ sheretz is in the משקה? mashke? Correct. But does not
touch the bottom of the כלי? kli? Yes. Because you've dangled it
in the משקה mashke without touching the כלי. kli. Right. It's floating.
By the way,
if you take that שרץ sheretz out and you put it in
another כלי, kli, the שרץ sheretz could still do the same thing?
שרץ sheretz never depletes its ability to make something טמא. tamei.
No, I don't think so, no.
It's an infinite potential. It's like an ever-ready battery.
Well, at some point if it disintegrates, it's no longer intact.
I don't understand the biology, but yeah, that's interesting actually though. At
what point when it loses its.
Well, that's my point. Sort of like the moldy, the moldy, you
know, that's what I'm trying to say. Like the disgusting water in
the insides of the cow.
How about the skeleton of the שרץ? sheretz?
Right, let's say it was eaten by something else, you know, then
it would probably be סרוח saruach at some point.
שרץ סרוח, sheretz saruach, yeah, very good. It
would rot.
But we learned if the cow drank that rotten מי חטאת, mei
chatat, we're saying it got absorbed somehow.
We didn't necessarily say it became absorbed, we said it became, you
know, disgusting. Yeah, סרוח במעיה.
saruach b'mei'eha.
Right, then it becomes בטל batel from טומאה, tumah, but because it
became into a something disgusting.
So
why does that have to be in the
first place is disgusting, is
סרוח, saruach, yeah.
Okay,
anyway, so I don't want us to get too far afield because
it's already 8:15 and we're still on עמוד א'. amud aleph. So,
okay, but the point is, so we're still trying to prove whether,
you know, how do we know? I mean, we know what they
said. We're trying to now, we're sort of working backwards, how do
we know that that's the case? So how do we know that
if I have a שרץ sheretz in this משקה mashke itself that
it can't be מטמא metameh
a כלי? kli? Okay, so then the answer is, משקה הבא מחמת
שרץ מי כתיבי? mashke haba machmat sheretz mi ketivi? That
that's not our case of the פסוקים. pesukim.
So is that even mentioned? No, it's not, right?
Our point was again, you know, you have this in the airspace
of it. Okay, but so what? It's not mentioned in those פסוקים.
pesukim. לאו בקל וחומר אתי? lav bekal vachomer ati? ומה משקה הבא
מחמת כלי
מטמא, umah mashke haba machmat kli metamei,
right? So if
even, again, what was our case? Our case was that you dangle
the שרץ sheretz in the, let's say, the airspace of a כלי
חרס, kli cheres, right? And the כלי חרס kli cheres becomes טמא.
tamei. Now the משקין mashkin in it are טמא, tamei, right? So
that's our case. משקה הבא מחמת כלי, mashke haba machmat kli, right?
Because they're, because they're, you know, in the כלי kli that's טמא.
tamei. So now they become
מטמא metameh other things, like let's say אוכלין. ochlin. Then משקה הבא
מחמת שרץ לא כל שכן? mashke haba machmat sheretz lo kol shekein?
Wouldn't you say it's a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? I understand the
תורה Torah isn't saying it, but so what? It's a קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, right?
So then it should certainly be, so just like the כלי kli
becomes טמא tamei in the first case, right? משקה הבא מחמת שרץ
לא כל שכן?
mashke haba machmat
sheretz lo kol shekein? You know,
so shouldn't I say that if this שרץ sheretz directly touches the
משקה mashke it should be מטמא metamei the כלי? kli?
Right, right. If the כלי kli makes it טמא, tamei, the שרץ
sheretz certainly makes it טמא. tamei.
Right, that's the קל וחומר, kal vachomer, right? If the כלי kli
is מטמא, metameh certainly
the שרץ sheretz is מטמא. metameh, Right. Yes.
What if you take a dead שרץ sheretz and dangle it into
an empty כלי kli and then put משקין mashkin in it? Is
the משקין mashkin טמא? tamei?
Where's the שרץ? sheretz? Still dangling? So it doesn't.
Yeah, I would think, I would think it would be the same
thing. Because the point is the כלי kli now becomes טמא. tamei.
It's like now טמא. tamei.
Yeah, you wave it in the air, then you take it out,
then you pour water in there, the water's טמא. tamei.
Yeah, because it goes through the air, so the air, the כלי
kli has now become טמא tamei
in the אויר avir of the כלי, kli, right.
Okay,
so now it makes sense. That's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. But
the problem is it's not what we said, right? I mean, their
opinion was that they are not מטמא. metameh. What about this קל
וחומר? kal vachomer? Shouldn't it make sense? So the answer is very,
very, very important: דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנדון. dayo l'va min
hadin lihyot kenidon. Right? In other words, we don't necessarily say קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. It's very interesting how sometimes we do and sometimes
we don't, you know? So basically the point is,
just like in our first case, right? You know, the dangling שרץ
sheretz in the כלי kli whatever, so only food, a food item
can be, can become טמא. tamei. and not the utensils. So so
too in in this case where the שרץ sheretz touched the water
directly, right? No, it can only מטמא metamei. food, not not כלים,
kelim, because that was that was the only case we had before.
Our only precedent was that foods can can be טמא, tamei, which
is that whole פסוק pasuk that can be
done, taken
only as far as מטמא.
metamei This whole thing about this קל וחומר kal vachomer is about
the relationship between disparate entities. דיו dayo is saying you're assuming that
there's potentially a hierarchy between these two separate entities, but actually they're
the same.
Right, the only case law, a strict constructionist view, the only case
law that we had was that אכל, ochel, a food, call it
food or drink, whatever, but you know, a food substance can be
טמא, tamei, right? And that was our whole case, the dangling שרץ
sheretz in there, whatever's in there, becomes טמא, tamei, right? The Torah's
case was not actually putting the שרץ sheretz in the water itself.
We said oh that should be a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? No,
the case was it can מטמא metamei. another food. Okay, so let's
say in our non-Torah case, you put the שרץ sheretz in the
water, so that can מטמא metamei another food, can't be מטמא כלי.
metamei kli. That's דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנידון. dayo lavah min
hadin lihyot kenidon. Just like we saw that something can מטמא metamei
an אכל, ochel, so too this will מטמא metamei an אכל. ochel.
It cannot be מטמא כלי. metamei kli. That's what this is. Okay.
That was all this יטמא yitamei thing, right? So
okay, so getting back to this.
Now Rabbi Akiva. So יטמא דרישא היכי דרש? yitamei de'reisha heichi darash?
Remember we had two יטמאs, yitamei right? There was the first part
and the second part. מכל אכל אשר יאכל אשר יבוא עליו מים
יטמא.
mikol ochel asher yei'achel asher
yavo alav mayim yitamei. This is somewhat of the same thing again.
Why you should need the two יטמאs, yitamei right? Because it's not
a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you can't learn it from a קל
וחומר kal vachomer anymore because you just said דיו.
dayo. Okay and all this was Rabbi Yosei. He expounded Rabbi Akiva.
He's saying oh that's how he knew it, but Akiva didn't actually
say any of that, right? He just said that it makes a
שלישי בחולין. shelishi bechulin. That's what he said, right?
So what does Akiva do with it? That's our question.
Okay, so what does Akiva himself do? Right, all this was Rabbi
Yosei's דרש derash on this on Rabbi Akiva. Because Rabbi Akiva elsewhere
he had this יטמא yitamei of יטמא. yitamei. So so too he
applied it to this case. So now that's Rabbi Yosei, great. What
does Rabbi Akiva do with it? So because again we said that
the two are not, you know, analogous. We said Rabbi Yosei said
it in the שיטה shita of Rabbi Akiva but he doesn't necessarily
agree with him, you know. So יטמא דרישא היכי דרש? yitamei de'reisha
heichi darash? So מכל אכל אשר יאכל אשר יבוא עליו מים יטמא.
mikol ochel asher yei'achel asher yavo alav mayim yitamei. יטמא לטמא את
המשקין.
yitamei letamei et
hamashkin. Okay so that's, which is sort of what we were saying
before.
Again, we're going to go through more or less the same exercise.
But so okay it comes into contact with אכל, ochel, right, and
it was נכשר במים nichshar bemayim
יטמא, yitamei,
so it will טמא את המשקין. tamei et hamashkin. As we said,
אכל ochel can be מטמא משקין metamei mashkin. but not like and
like, we're still saying that. לטמא את המשקין ואינו אלא לטמא את
הכלי. letamei et hamashkin ve'eino ela letamei et hakli. So same idea.
So how do we know it's just לטמא את המשקה, letamei et
hamashke, how do we know it's not to be
מטמא את הכלי? metamei et hakli? So אמרת קל וחומר: amarta kal
vachomer: ומשקה שמטמא אוכל אינו מטמא כלי. umashke shemetamei ochel eino metamei
kli. So just like a משקה mashke is מטמא metamei an אוכל
ochel but it's not מטמא כלי, metamei kli, just like we mentioned
all above because דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנידון. dayo lavah min
hadin lihyot kenidon. אוכל שאין מטמא אוכל אינו דין שלא יטמא כלי?
ochel she'ein metamei ochel eino
din shelo yetamei kli? It's the inverse. It's the inverse קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Right.
You now do it, you can do קל וחומר kal vachomer in
the negative. Right.
So basically we're saying, of course it can't be מטמא את הכלי.
metamei et hakli. Of course.
How would you even think that, a קל וחומר kal vachomer that
it wouldn't, right? Just like a משקה mashke is מטמא metamei an
אוכל ochel but not a כלי, kli, like we just said, we
were mentioning before. So certainly an אוכל ochel that can't be מטמא
metamei an אוכל, ochel, right?
Because like can't be
מטמא metamei like. So
of
course אינו דין שלא יטמא כלי. eino din shelo yetamei kli. So
הא מה אני מקיים
יטמא?
ha ma ani
mekayem yitamei? So then what can it be מטמא? metamei לטמא את
המשקין, letamei et hamashkin, right? So obviously that's what's left, right? So
Buddy says שהן עלול לקבל
טומאה. shehein alul lekabel tumah. That's a little bit strange. He's saying
the reason, so at the beginning he's saying these אוכלין ochalin can
be מטמא את המשקין metamei et hamashkin because it's susceptible. They're prone,
right? They have a predisposition to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So
the question is מה אריא משקה משום דעלול לקבל טומאה? ma arya
mashke mishum de'alul lekabel tumah? Because they're predisposed? תיפוק ליה משום דליכא
מידי אחרינא, teipuk lei mishum delika midi achrina, right? What else is
there, right? We've already said,
like can't be מטמא metamei? like because we said that, we never
see it anywhere else. And we went through this whole קל וחומר
kal vachomer that it can't be מטמא את הכלי, metamei et hakli,
right? So what else is there? The only thing there is left
is that,
is
מטמא משקין. metamei mashkin. Why do you need to say it's
עלול? alul? Forget about the reason why. It's not like you're logically
figuring this out like oh it's because it's גזירת הכתוב. gezeiras hakatuv.
It's because that's what it is. There's nothing else, right? So then
הכי
קאמר. hachi kaamar. This is getting back to your
question from before. וכי תימא אוכל חמור דמטמא משקין, vichi teima ochel
chamur dematamei mashkin, which is more חמור, chamur, right? On the hierarchy
of things. You say okay maybe אוכל ochel is more חמור chamur
because it מטמא metamei משקין. mashkin Therefore it should be מטמא לכלי.
metamei lekli. So
we see אוכל מטמא משקין ochel metamei mashkin maybe it's more חמור
chamur should be
מטמא לכלי. metamei lekli. No, חומרא דמשקין הוא. chumra demashkin hu. The
whole reason why אוכל ochel may seem it's more חמור chamur is
not because אוכל ochel itself is more חמור. chamur. It's because it
came in contact with משקין mashkin at some point.
It's a חומרא דמשקין
chumra
demashkin
משום דמשקין הוא דקבל טומאה mishum demashkin hu dekabel tumah because משקין
mashkin itself can
be prone to acquiring טומאה. tumah. What do you mean?
משקין mashkin are more susceptible to טומאה tumah than אוכלין.
ochlin.
And that makes
משקין מטמא אוכל.
mashkin metamei ochel. Yeah. Stronger,
yes. And how do we see that?
משום דמשקין דקבל טומאה. mishum demashkin dekabel tumah. How are they more
prone for this טומאה? tumah? ומה היא עדיפותן umah hi adifutan שקבלת
טומאה שלא בהכשר shekabalas tumah shelo behechsher
because foods have to be prepared, just like Rifka was saying. Foods
have to be prepared to receive טומאה tumah by being wetted. Yeah
and your whole question was do you need the intention, do you
not, are you happy about it? That's something else. But they still
have to be prepared, right?
But we don't see that beverage, you don't have to prepare your
beverage. The beverage is the beverage, right? If a dead שרץ sheretz
falls in it, that's the end of it, right? You don't have
to have a הכנה hachanah in my mind.
Well, it works both ways, right? Why did the כהנים kohanim do
נטילת ידים? netilas yadayim? Why did they wash? What was the purpose
to wash?
Because we said that that's גזירה דרבנן gezeirah derabbanan because the רבנן
rabbanan were גוזר gozer the ידים yadayim as a שני לקבל טומאה.
sheni lekabel tumah. Right. So and a שני sheni can be and
they also a separate גזירה gezeira that a שני sheni can make
if it touches something else can upgrade it. Although usually we downgrade,
it can be, it can even be upgraded. I think in the
case of water. That was like to a ראשון. rishon.
And then so washing hands would do what?
Remove טומאת ידים. tumas yadayim.
וטהר, vetaher, right?
It removes the rabbinic טומאת ידים. tumas yadayim.
It's as if they're putting the hands in a מקוה. mikvah. Yeah.
It's basically bringing the מקוה mikvah to you.
Right. If you look at it that way.
That's the procedure for removing טומאת ידים. tumas yadayim. That's why there
has to be a minimum amount of water for נטילת ידים. netilas
yadayim.
Sensible.
Why did you say that הכנה... hachanah...
Okay yeah so let me get back to, let me just articulate
this point. So again
so we basically are saying that in the end of the day
משקין mashkin are more חמור. chamur. How so? Because משקה mashkeh can
be מכשיר אוכל machshir ochel if it falls on it, right? But
משקה mashkeh itself doesn't need any הכנה, hachanah, right? It's not like
the משקה mashkeh has to come in contact with טמא משקה. tamei
mashkeh.
In other words, when you say הכנה hachanah what do you mean?
In other words how does the food become טמא? tamei? Right that's
the whole point, right? Didn't you... your whole point was it didn't
need to come...
המשקה hamashkeh makes it...
Exactly. Right right. So but that's a חומרא chumra because of משקה
mashkeh because the משקה mashkeh fell on the food. Now the food
should something now טמא tamei fall on it or be in the
airspace of a whatever, it can be טמא. tamei. Right. So משקה
mashkeh is preparing the food. But nothing prepares the משקה mashkeh itself.
It just is.
By its nature. Right. So that's why we're saying it's משקה mashkeh
is more חמור, chamur, right? Because
שקבלת טומאה שלא בהכשר. shekabalas tumah shelo behechsher. You don't need something
preparing this משקה mashkeh itself to become טמא. tamei.
Just by its nature.
Right. In other words the dead... what we're saying is let's say
the שרץ sheretz fell on the food that never had water on
it, it wouldn't become טמא. tamei. Forget the כלי חרס kli cheres
for a moment, right? But if the שרץ sheretz falls on your
wine or
on a dry apple
that never had dew, never had water on it, I plucked it
right now, put it on the table and the dead שרץ sheretz
was touching the apples from the time they were plucked. And that's
what I asked you before and you said no it had to
have had dew on it.
Yeah it did.
Yeah. But if it didn't...
If it didn't, right, then it's not. Right.
Yeah. But no but I'm asking... before I...
Right right right.
So but the משקה mashkeh itself doesn't need anything preparing it, right?
The משקה mashkeh prepares the
אוכל. ochel. That's the point. Right, exactly the point here.
It's wet... it is wetness.
Right. Okay,
so let's go on a little further. יטמא yitma דאין עושה כיוצא
בה. deein oseh kayotzei bah.
So יטמא yitma the next בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you guys are
going
to be right there because you'll know it
all.
There's a
difference between knowing and remembering it.
So the question is do you want me to go on or
do you want me to stop? 8:30
I mean we're almost
at... So far in because the concept. It's very hard. It's hard.
All
right,
I think it seems like people want to. Tomorrow? I'm up for
tomorrow. Yeah. It's
very hard.
It's hard. All right, let's stop.
We'll stop now. I think people have had enough. Good
stuff,
Michael. It's very hard. Yes, Michael.